Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine Collection 1918-1992 1946-1988
ML31.K397
Kaye, Danny
Fine, Sylvia
approximately 89,161 items
794 containers
4 mapcase folders
257.75 linear feet
Music Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Danny Kaye (1911-1987) was an American actor, singer, dancer, comedian, and humanitarian. His wife, Sylvia Fine (1913-1991), was an American lyricist, composer, writer, lecturer, and producer. The collection, which documents their lives and careers, contains printed and manuscript music, scripts, correspondence, business and financial papers, promotional and publicity materials, speeches, oral history transcripts, photographs, scrapbooks, programs, posters, honors, and realia.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Allan, Rupert, 1913-1991--Correspondence.; Allen, Steve, 1921-2000--Correspondence.; Bass, Jules--Correspondence.; Bavasi, Buzzie--Correspondence.; Beatrix, Queen of the Netherlands, 1938- --Correspondence.; Behrendt, Olive--Correspondence.; Bernhard, Prince, consort of Juliana, Queen of the Netherlands, 1911-2004--Correspondence.; Brademas, John, 1927-2016--Correspondence.; Brown, David, 1916-2010--Correspondence.; Brown, Helen Gurley--Correspondence.; Campion, Clifford--Correspondence.; Carlisle, Kitty, 1910-2007--Correspondence.; Chen, Joyce--Correspondence.; Chevalier, Maurice, 1888-1972--Correspondence.; Child, Julia--Correspondence.; Claiborne, Craig--Correspondence.; Colbert, Claudette--Correspondence.; Craig, David, 1923-1998--Correspondence.; Cunningham, Marion--Correspondence.; De Mille, Agnes--Correspondence.; Dickson, Harry Ellis--Correspondence.; Douglas, Kirk, 1916-2020--Correspondence.; Eban, Abba Solomon, 1915-2002--Correspondence.; Elizabeth II, Queen of Great Britain, 1926-2022--Correspondence.; Elizabeth, Queen, consort of George VI, King of Great Britain, 1900-2002--Correspondence.; Fairbanks, Douglas, Jr., 1909-2000--Correspondence.; Fine, Sylvia--Archives.; Fine, Sylvia--Correspondence.; Fine, Sylvia--Photographs.; Fine, Sylvia.; Fine, Sylvia.; Fine, Sylvia. Works. Selections.; George VI, King of Great Britain, 1895-1952--Correspondence.; Gordon, Ruth, 1896-1985--Correspondence.; Graham, Katharine, 1917-2001--Correspondence.; Grant, Cary, 1904-1986--Correspondence.; Green, Johnny, 1908-1989--Correspondence.; Halsman, Philippe.; Hitzing, Holly, 1910-1998--Correspondence.; Hoffman, Anna Rosenberg, 1902-1983--Correspondence.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978--Correspondence.; Jackson, Anne, 1925-2016--Correspondence.; Javits, Jacob K. (Jacob Koppel), 1904-1986--Correspondence.; Jewison, Norman, 1926-2024--Correspondence.; Kan, Johnny--Correspondence.; Kanin, Garson, 1912-1999--Correspondence.; Kaye, Danny--Archives.; Kaye, Danny--Caricatures and cartoons.; Kaye, Danny--Correspondence.; Kaye, Danny--Performances.; Kaye, Danny--Photographs.; Kaye, Danny.; Kaye, Danny.; Kaye, Dena--Correspondence.; Kaye, Dena--Photographs.; Kingman, Dong, 1911- --Correspondence.; Kingsley, Ben, 1943- --Correspondence.; Kollek, Teddy, 1911-2007--Correspondence.; Lasker, Mary--Correspondence.; Marriott, Vi--Correspondence.; McCarthy, Frank, 1912-1986--Correspondence.; McDowall, Roddy--Correspondence.; McDowall, Roddy.; Nassikas, James--Correspondence.; Olivier, Laurence, 1907-1989--Correspondence.; Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1929-1994--Correspondence.; Ormandy, Eugene, 1899-1985--Correspondence.; Panama, Norman--Correspondence.; Peck, Gregory, 1916-2003--Correspondence.; Philip, Prince, consort of Elizabeth II, Queen of Great Britain, 1921-2021--Correspondence.; Pons, Lily, 1898-1976--Correspondence.; Pépin, Jacques--Correspondence.; Rabb, Maxwell M., 1910-2002--Correspondence.; Rabin, Yitzhak, 1922-1995--Correspondence.; Reagan, Nancy, 1921-2016--Correspondence.; Ribicoff, Abraham, 1910-1998--Correspondence.; Roebling, Mary G. 1905-1994--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962--Correspondence.; Scully, Vin, 1927- --Correspondence.; Selznick, Irene Mayer, 1907-1990--Correspondence.; Shaw, Run Run, 1907-2014--Correspondence.; Shore, Dinah, 1917-1994--Correspondence.; Sills, Beverly--Correspondence.; Smith, Oliver Lemuel, 1918-1994--Correspondence.; Swaffer, Hannen, 1879-1962--Correspondence.; Valenti, Jack--Correspondence.; Walker, Nancy, 1922-1992--Correspondence.; Wallach, Eli, 1915-2014--Correspondence.; Wences, Señor, 1896-1999--Correspondence.; Will, George F.--Correspondence.; Zāhidī, Ardashīr, 1928-2021--Correspondence.
Organizations
Dena Pictures, Inc.; Dena Pictures, Inc.; Kaye (Danny)/Fine (Sylvia) Collection (Library of Congress) DLC; Los Angeles Dodgers (Baseball team); UNICEF.; United Service Organizations (U.S.)
Subjects
Baseball--Songs and music.; Baseball.; Comedians--United States.; Cooking, Chinese.; Cooking, Italian.; Entertainers--United States.; Motion picture music--Excerpts--Scores.; Motion pictures--United States; Music--Manuscripts.; Musical films--United States.; Musical theater--United States.; Musicals--Librettos.; Musicals--United States--Excerpts.; Musicals--United States.; Popular music--United States.; Revues--United States.; Songs--Texts.; Television music--Excerpts--Scores.; Television--Production and direction--United States.; Theater--United States.; Women composers--United States.; Women librettists--United States.
Titles
Court jester (Motion picture); Court jester (Motion picture); Danny Kaye show (Radio program); Danny Kaye show (Television program); Danny Kaye show (Television program); Five pennies (Motion picture); Five pennies (Motion picture); Hans Christian Andersen (Motion picture); Hans Christian Andersen (Motion picture); Inspector general (Motion picture: 1949); John Gary show.; John Gary show.; Knock on wood (Motion picture); Knock on wood (Motion picture); Madwoman of Chaillot (Motion picture); Madwoman of Chaillot (Motion picture); Me and the Colonel (Motion picture); Me and the Colonel (Motion picture); Merry Andrew (Motion picture); Merry Andrew (Motion picture); Musical comedy tonight II.; Musical comedy tonight II.; Musical comedy tonight III.; Musical comedy tonight III.; Musical comedy tonight.; Musical comedy tonight.; On the double (Motion picture); On the double (Motion picture); On the Riviera (Motion picture); On the Riviera (Motion picture); Secret life of Walter Mitty (Motion picture: 1947); Secret life of Walter Mitty (Motion picture: 1947); Up in arms (Motion picture); Up in arms (Motion picture); White Christmas (Motion picture: 1954); White Christmas (Motion picture: 1954); Wonder man (Motion picture); Wonder man (Motion picture)
Form/Genre
Address books.; Artifacts (Object genre); Awards.; Clippings (Information artifacts); Contracts.; Correspondence.; Financial records.; Lecture notes.; Notes.; Photographic prints.; Posters.; Programs (Documents); Promotional materials.; Scores.; Scrapbooks.; Scripts (Documents); Speeches.; Variety shows (Radio programs); Variety shows (Television programs); Writings (Documents)
Provenance
Gift, Sylvia Fine, 1990; Gift, Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine Kaye Foundation, 1992, 2010-2013; Gift, Dena Kaye 2019-2020.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
Audiovisual materials were transferred to the Library of Congress Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division. Some of the audiovisual materials have been cataloged separately and are identified as part of the Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine Collection (Library of Congress) (MAVIS no. 3851).
Six maps from the Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine collection were transferred to the Library of Congress Geography and Maps Division in 2021. An inventory of this transferred material is available in the Music Division's collection file.
One hundred and fifteen items from the Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine collection including postcards, artworks, bound volumes, photographs, and ephemera were transferred to the Library of Congress Prints and Photographs Division in 2023. An inventory of this transferred material is available in the Music Division's collection file.
One volume from the Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine collection was transferred to the Library of Congress Rare Books and Special Collections Division in 2024. An inventory of this material is available in the Music Division's collection file.
Published, typescript, and photocopied versions of musical comedy play scripts collected by Sylvia Fine for use in teaching and producing television programs on musical comedy were separated from the Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine Collection. They now constitute the Sylvia Fine Musical Comedy Library Scripts.
Other Repositories
Special collections at the University of Michigan holds the Holly Fine and Danny Kaye Papers.
Related Material
The following Library of Congress collections contain Danny Kaye and/or Sylvia Fine correspondence, photographs, scripts, and oral history transcripts:
Irving Berlin Collection
Leonard Bernstein Collection
Hume Cronyn and Jessica Tandy Papers
Burt Boyar Collection of Sammy Davis Jr. Biographical Material
Jerry Valburn Collection on Duke Ellington
Sylvia Fine Musical Comedy Library Scripts
Bob Fosse and Gwen Verdon Collection
Ira and Leonore S. Gershwin Trust Archive
Ruth Gordon and Garson Kanin Papers
Andre Kostelanetz Collection
Burton Lane Papers
Joshua Logan Papers
Look Magazine Picture Research File (Library of Congress)
Clare Booth Luce Papers
Henry Mancini Papers
Vincent Price Papers
Access and Restrictions
The Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine Collection is open to research. The bulk of the collection is in off-site storage and researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Persons granted access to the collection may procure single-copy reproductions of the unpublished materials in the collection, provided they have secured the written consent of the Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine Kaye Foundation and/or other lawful owners of the intellectual property interests.
Online Content
Selected materials from the Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine Collection are available on the Library of Congress website at https://www.loc.gov/collections/danny-kaye-and-sylvia-fine/about-this-collection/.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1911, Jan. 18 David Daniel Kaminsky born, Brooklyn, New York Youngest of three sons and first native-born American born to Clara and Jacob Kaminsky, both originally from Ukraine; all three brothers eventually changed their names: Mack became Max Kamin and Larry became Larry Kaye
1913, Aug. 29 Sylvia Harriet Fine born, Brooklyn, New York One of three children born to Bessie and Dr. Samuel Fine, a dentist; son Robert later changed name to Robert Forrest
circa 1917 David Kaminsky entered PS 149, Brooklyn, New York
1919 Fine began piano lessons
1923 Fine began studying harmony and musical theory Fine developed fear of performing in front of large audiences; became interested in writing and composing
circa 1925 Dr. Samuel Fine employed David Kaminsky for a short period David and Sylvia met briefly
circa 1927 1930 David Kaminsky attended Thomas Jefferson High School; left without graduating
1928 Fine graduated from Thomas Jefferson High School Fine enrolled in Hunter College to study music; took courses at Brooklyn campus (which became Brooklyn College in 1930)
1930 David Kaminsky took stage name of "Danny Kaye" Kaye performed as a tummler at White Roe Lake summer resort, Catskill Mountains, New York; as a jester did comedy, sang, other entertainment between acts
1933 Kaye toured Far East with Dave Harvey and Kathleen Young as the Three Terpsichoreans Kaye began to craft double-talk, babbling, and dialect routines
1937 Kaye signed with Educational Pictures to appear in two-reel comedies; made three short films intended to be shown between features
1939 Kaye and Fine met again while working on the unsuccessful Max Liebman production Saturday Night Vanities Liebman hired Fine to write specialty material for Camp Tamiment, a Pennsylvania summer camp Camp Tamiment hired Kaye on Fine's recommendation Fine wrote "The Wolf of Wall Street" (Yiddish version of Gilbert and Sullivan's Mikado ), "Stanislavsky," and "Pavlowa," along with other material specifically for Kaye Kaye and Fine made Broadway debuts in Liebman's Straw Hat Revue, which featured "Anatole of Paris" in addition to the material Fine created at Camp Tamiment
1940, Jan. 13 Kaye and Fine married, Fort Lauderdale, Florida
1940, Feb. 22 Kaye and Fine married again in formal New York City wedding ceremony with family present
1940 Kaye performed Fine's material, including "Anatole of Paris," at Manhattan nightclub La Martinique
1941, Jan. 23 Kaye starred in Moss Hart's Lady in the Dark, in which he performed "Tchaikovsky," written by Hart and Ira Gershwin
1941, Oct. 29 Kaye starred in Cole Porter's Let's Face It!, in which he performed "Melody in 4F" by Fine and Liebman
1943, Mar. 1 Fine and Kaye negotiated five-year movie contract for Kaye with Samuel Goldwyn
1943 Kaye legally changed name to Danny Kaye
1944 Feb. Kaye starred in first feature film, Up in Arms, which included Fine and Liebman's "The Lobby Number" and "Melody in 4F"
1945 Kaye appeared in second feature film, Wonder Man, performing Fine's "Bali Boogie"
1945 1946 CBS radio aired The Danny Kaye Show (subtitled "Pabst Blue Ribbon Time"); Fine served as executive producer and created musical numbers for all 50 episodes
1945 1967 Kaye entertained troops in Japan, Korea, and Vietnam as part of USO tours with Leo Durocher (1940s and 1950s) and Vikki Carr (1966-1967), among others
1946, Dec. 17 Daughter Dena born (Kaye and Fine's only child)
1946 The Kid from Brooklyn released; Kaye performed "Pavlowa" by Fine Kaye began performance tour in the United States between filming dates
1947 Kaye starred in The Secret Life of Walter Mitty, performing musical numbers by Fine, including "Anatole of Paris" and "A New Symphony for Unstrung Tongue"
1948 A Song is Born released, featuring Kaye with Louis Armstrong, Benny Goodman, and Lionel Hampton; not considered a box office success, the film is Kaye's first in which there is no material by Fine Kaye played six-week engagement at the London Palladium
1949 Kaye starred in The Inspector General, his first Warner Brothers film; Fine's contributions include "The Gypsy Drinking Song" and "Soliloquy for Three Heads" Kaye and Fine ended their contract with Warner Brothers after the poor reception of The Inspector General and signed with 20th Century-Fox Kaye's first album, Danny Kaye, released by Columbia; tracks include "Deenah," "Minnie the Moocher," and Fine's "Anatole of Paris"
1950 Kaye starred in On the Riviera, a 20th Century-Fox release, which included four songs by Fine; Kaye received Goldon Globe Award for Best Performance by an Actor in a Motion Picture - Comedy or Musical
1952 Kaye starred in Hans Christian Andersen, a Goldwyn Studios production
1953 Kaye played eight-week engagement at the Palace Theatre on Broadway Fine and Herschel Burke Gilbert's song "The Moon is Blue," from the movie of the same name, nominated for an Academy Award as Best Song
1954 Kaye named United Nations Children's Fund's (UNICEF) first Goodwill Ambassador to the world's children, beginning a 33-year relationship with the organization Kaye's international visits with underprivileged children documented in the UNICEF film, Assignment: Children Kaye co-starred with Bing Crosby in White Christmas
1954 1986 Kaye conducted Philadelphia Orchestra in his first classical music concert; over next 32 years, raises nearly $10 million for musicians' pension funds by conducting concerts around the world
1955 Kaye received special Academy Award for his humanitarian efforts Kaye received first honorary degree, Doctor of Humanitites, from American International College, Springfield, Massachusetts; he would receive seven more during his lifetime Fine an uncredited co-writer with Elmer Bernstein of the main title song for Man with a Golden Arm, for which Bernstein received an Academy Award
1956 Kaye performed Fine's material in the movie The Court Jester The Secret Life of Danny Kaye, a film documenting Kaye's work for UNICEF, aired on CBS as an episode of See It Now; the program earned Kaye a Peabody Award for the promotion of international understanding
1957 Kaye starred in Merry Andrew
1958 Columbia Pictures released Kaye's film, Me and the Colonel for which he received a Golden Globe Award for Best Performance by an Actor in a Motion Picture - Comedy Or Musical Brooklyn College named Fine Alumna of the Year
1958 1985 Kaye-Smith Enterprises, a joint venture with Lester M. Smith, was formed. Over its history, it owned and operated radio stations in Washington, Oregon, Kansas, and Ohio. Related businesses included the promotion company Concerts West and Kaye-Smith Productions, a recording and film production firm. Smith bought out all of Kaye's interests in 1985
1959 Kaye starred in The Five Pennies, featuring music by Fine, including "Lullaby in Ragtime;" Fine's song "The Five Pennies" nominated for an Academy Award as Best Song
1960 Kaye performed for four weeks at The Desert Inn in first appearance in Las Vegas Kaye starred in, and Fine produced, his first television special, An Hour with Danny Kaye, which was nominated for an Emmy Award Kaye obtained his pilot's license
1961 Kaye made On the Double Kaye starred in his second television special, The Danny Kaye Show
1962 Kaye starred in The Man from the Diner's Club Kaye starred in his third television special, The Danny Kaye Show with Lucille Ball
1963 Kaye visited the U.S.S.R. for the United States Information Agency and to attend the Moscow Film Festival
1963 1967 Kaye's weekly variety television series, The Danny Kaye Show, aired on CBS; it received Peabody Award, and Emmy Awards for Best Musical Variety Star and Best Variety Program, and numerous Emmy nominations
1965 Kaye part of official UNICEF delegation at the Nobel Peace Prize award ceremony Kaye earned flight instrument rating
1965 1975 Kaye made four flying trips throughout the United States in support of Trick-or-Treat for UNICEF; on last trip, he visited 65 cities in the United States and Canada in five days
1966 Kaye became vice-president of Lear Jet Kaye received Medal of the Ville de Paris
1967 1968 Kaye made seven-week tour across four continents conducting the Gadna Israeli Youth Orchestra
1969 Kaye appeared in last feature film, The Madwoman of Chaillot
1970, Nov. 10 1971, Sept. 11 Kaye starred in Richard Rodgers stage musical Two by Two
1971 1973 Kaye co-starred in television musicals Peter Pan, Peter Cottontail, and Pinocchio
1972 Fine taught semester-long musical comedy course at the University of Southern California
1974 CBS televised Kaye's Look-In at the Metropolitan Opera; Fine received Emmy Award as the program's producer
1975 Fine taught semester-long musical comedy course at Yale University Kaye received Les Meilleurs Ouvriers de France, the first non-professional to receive France's top culinary award
1979 Kaye part of original ownership group of Major League Baseball's Seattle Mariners PBS broadcasted Fine's Musical Comedy Tonight, documentary based on her lecture series; she received personal Peabody Award for the program
1981 Kaye appeared in Fine's Musical Comedy Tonight II Kaye starred in the television movie Skokie Kaye received a personal Peabody Award for Skokie and An Evening with Danny Kaye and The New York Philharmonic
1982 Kaye received Jean Hersholt Humanitarian Award from the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences
1983 Kaye received Screen Actors' Guild Lifetime Achievement Award Queen Margrethe II of Denmark awarded Kaye the Cross of the Knight of the Dannebrog, 1st Class, for his work with UNICEF and longstanding ties with Denmark
1984 Jan. Kaye served as Grand Marshall of the Pasadena Tournament of Roses Parade
1984 Dec. Kaye received Kennedy Center Honor, along with Lena Horne, Isaac Stern, Gian Carlo Menotti, and Arthur Miller
1985 PBS aired Fine's Musical Comedy Tonight III Fine received the Division of Drama's Lifetime Achievement Award from the University of Southern California Fine received honorary Doctorate of Humane Letters from Brooklyn College Kaye received honorary Doctorate of Humane Letters from the University of South Carolina
1986 French Republic named Kaye Chevalier of the Legion of Honor
1987 1991 Under Fine's direction, Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine Kaye Foundation funded refurbishment of Playhouse at Hunter College, which became the Sylvia and Danny Kaye Playhouse at its reopening in 1993
1987, Mar. 2 Kaye died, Los Angeles, California
1987, June 23 Kaye posthumously received Presidential Medal of Freedom Columbia University and Tufts University posthumously conferred honorary doctorates on Kaye
1988 Long Island University awarded Fine honorary doctorate in Humane Letters
1991 Apr. Fine endowed the Sylvia Fine Chair in Musical Theater at Brooklyn College
1991, Oct. 29 Fine died, New York City
Scope and Content Note
The Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine Collection documents the life and work of actor, singer, dancer, and comedian, Danny Kaye, and his wife, lyricist, composer, writer, lecturer, and producer, Sylvia Fine. It spans the period 1918-1992, with the bulk of the materials falling between 1946 and 1988, and includes manuscript and printed music, scripts, correspondence, business and financial papers, promotional and publicity materials, speeches, oral history transcripts, photographs and iconography, programs, posters, clippings, honors, and realia.
Although the collection is quite extensive, it is not comprehensive. Outgoing correspondence is scarce and there are few documents in Kaye's hand. There is little documentation of Kaye's early performing career with the Three Terpsichoreans, his New York nightclub work, or Kaye and Fine's Broadway activities in the 1940s. Kaye's recording career is similarly undocumented beyond several album covers and photographs of recording sessions. However, the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division holds a significant quantity of audiovisual materials related to Kaye's recording career.
Music, in the form of scores, parts, orchestral arrangements, and sheet music, comprises the bulk of the collection. Most of this material was used in Kaye's performance tours, movies, stage productions, television specials, and his television series, The Danny Kaye Show, or was created for his films. Included are Kaye's trademark songs such as "Tchaikovsky," "The Dodgers Song," "Minnie the Moocher," and "Ballin' the Jack," as well as many other titles that he performed throughout his career. Music for The John Gary Show (1966), a summer replacement series for The Danny Kaye Show and selections from An Evening with Danny Kaye concerts are in the collection as well.
The collection also includes music manuscripts, printed music, and lyric sheets for songs written by Fine (alone or with others, including Sammy Cahn, Sy Miller, Vic Schoen, and Ben Weisman). Among these are "Anatole of Paris," "Life Could Not Better Be," "Melody in 4F," "Lullaby in Ragtime," and the main title for The Man with the Golden Arm, which Fine wrote with Elmer Bernstein. A number of Fine's sketchbooks are also included, in addition to sketch materials for the unfinished musical, We're a Whole New Thing. Management of Fine's music rights is documented in the Dena Music Files.